hey what's up guys my name is the
churner and welcome back to my stay plus
plus series I need a haircut so today
I'm gonna be talking all about objects
lifetimes I'm gonna kind of start
talking about memory and how objects
live specifically on these stack I am
going to make a heat versus tack video
in which we can actually talk about this
stuff in depth as well as probably
benchmark the difference in terms of
performance and just talk about all the
performance kind of metrics and and and
all that kind of stuff in that video but
today we're just gonna this is like a
gentle introduction to what lifetime
kind of means for stack-based variables
so there's kind of two parts to this
this this the first part is kind of you
have to understand how things live on
the stack in order for you to actually
be able to write code that doesn't crash
and code that works but also this actor
set the next step once you know how this
works is that I now know how to leverage
this and make it kind of do what I
wanted to do and come up with clever
ways to do things and we'll talk about
well we'll look at some examples of what
I mean by that today but basically we
have this concept of stacks how two
stacks well we'll have a web of video in
depth about that I know that I keep
saying we'll have a video for pretty
much every topic but it's just I don't
want to focus on the details of certain
elements in every video because
otherwise these videos we've 45 minutes
not helpful to people who already know
that stuff that's why I'm kind of trying
to monetize this series the best thing a
stack can be thought of as a data
structure in which you stack things on
top pretend that you've got a stack of
books on your desk in order for you to
actually access one in the middle you
would have to take the first few off to
get to that that book in the middle of
course in real life you could just yank
it out but that's not how stacks work in
programming so every time we enter a
scope in C++ we basically push us push
stack frame on it doesn't necessarily
have to be a stack frame in the case of
I'm actually pushing data on but you can
think of it as adding a book to your
pile and any variables that you declare
inside that scope is like writing stuff
into your book and once that scope ends
and you take that book off of your pile
of books it's gone right every stack
based variable which you declared in
that book every object that you created
on the stack inside that book they're
gone now and that is both a blessing and
a curse but if you know what you're
doing then obviously it's just
be a blessing 100% of the time right so
I'm going to show you some examples of
exactly how all of this comes together
and how all this works and hopefully
doesn't make it painfully obvious to you
so first of all let's talk about scopes
a scope can be anything from a function
scope like what this is right here some
kind of if statements cope like this or
could also be in a for loop or a while
loop or just an empty Scott like that we
also have scopes for classes meaning
that when I declare a class like entity
it's my go-to example and I have some
kind of stack initialized variable here
so something that isn't allocated on the
heap here then this variable is also
inside this class scope meaning that
when this class dies this variable dies
so let's see this in action I'm going to
just write a very simple entity class
here this doesn't have to be an empty
class could be absolutely anything it's
going to have a constructor here which
is going to print something to the
console like create identity and we're
also going to give this class a
destructor I'm actually just going to
copy this add the tilde here to make it
a destructor and change this to
destroyed entity so we have created
entity in a constructor and destroyed
entity in a destructor inside this scope
over here I'm going to declare my entity
instead of creating it on the heap on
guard credit on the stack just by
writing code like star this is going to
call the default constructor I'm going
to put a breakpoint on this line and hit
f5 to run my program okay so once I hit
this breakpoint I'm just going to open
my console here so that we can see
what's happening if I hit f10 to advance
one line forward you'll see the creative
entity gets printed to the console now
we are at the end of this scope here so
as soon as I hit f10 we are destroying
our entity that entity is gone now that
memory has been freed should be pretty
obvious if I was to do a heap allocation
on this by converting this into a
pointer and writing code like so with
optional parentheses if I hit f5 here
I'll have one line of code forward and
you can see that we didn't even go to
the scope here if I look at my console
we just say credit entity and that's it
we're already on this line I can even
execute this line so right now we're
actually waiting for input and you can
see our entity never gets destroyed of
course that memory does get cleaned up
by the operating system when our
application terminates so straight away
you should see the difference in object
lifetimes between a stack-based variable
and a heat-based variable
based variable gets freed gets destroyed
as soon as we go out of scope so that's
basically the point of today's video I
just want you to get it into your head
that if you declare something on the
stack if you create a variable on the
stack it's going to cease to exist when
it goes out of start now let's take a
look at some things you might not want
to do now that you have this knowledge a
great example is I want to create an
array inside a function maybe it's an
integer array so it will return an int
pointer I'll call this create array and
I might write code such as int array so
this is going to allocate the array 15
here to just large and then I can return
a raid now this looks like perfectly
sensible card I mean is creating an
array and then returning a pointer to
that array seems legit right wrong
you're completely wrong if you thought
that was legit I really hope you did
let's take a look at why so by creating
an array like this we're not allocating
on it on the heap we're not calling new
or doing some kind of heap allocation we
are just declaring it on the stack and
when we return a pointer to that is
returning a pointer to that stack memory
guess what that stack memory gets
cleared as soon as we go out of scope so
if you write code like this it's going
to fail if you would like to write a
function like this you basically have
two options you can either get this to
actually allocate the array on the heap
thus ensuring that its lifetime will
actually stay around or you could ask
this data that you've created here to
actually be copied to a location that
exists further up the stack so it has an
example let's say I actually create my
array over here of 50 integers and then
I want this credit ready to be more of a
fill array which would take in that
array as a parameter and actually do
anything that it had to do here of
course this example of creating an array
kind of falls apart since when I love
are creating it inside here but we are
still basically manipulating it so maybe
this could do something like fill our
array and in this sense we're just
passing a pointer so it's not going to
get de-allocated that array creation is
a classic mistake which I actually tend
to say all the time people will create a
stack based variable and try to return a
pointer to it
no realizing that once that function
ends and you go out of scope that
variables done so with this kind of
automatic destruction of stack based
variables is there a way that we can
kind of make it useful is there a way
that we can leverage it and use it for
good and the answer is yes there are
plenty of ways in which this is
incredibly useful and can actually help
kind of automate
code and one thing that we can do with
this is actually write scoped kind of
classes right such as a smart pointer
like unique pointer which is a scoped
pointer or something like a scoped lock
that there's a lot of examples which we
will definitely get into in the future
but the simplest example is probably a
stroked pointer what that basically is
is a class that's a wrapper over a
pointer which upon construction heap
allocates the pointer and then upon
destruction deletes the pointer so we
can kind of automate this new and delete
thing let's take a look at how we might
write a class like that so this entity
right I want to still allocated on the
heap I want to call new and all that
however I wanted to automatically be
deleted when this goes out of scope can
we do that the answer is yes so we could
use something in the standard library
called a unique pointer which is a
scoped pointer but for the purposes of
this example we'll write our own so that
you can see how it works
I write a class called scarf 2.0 I'm
going to keep it really simple for now
and just hog credit to only accept
entities so this will be our actual
pointer upon construction I'm going to
write a constructor which takes in our
entity so this is an MC point up I'm
going to assign s to here and upon
destruction I'm going to call delete and
point up just like that and that's it
that is a basic scoped pointer so let's
take a look at how we can use that
instead of writing entity a equals new
entity I'm actually going to ride scoped
pointer E which is basically our
variable name equals new entity I could
have also written this like so with the
default constructor but just to keep it
similar to what it was before it kind of
looks the same and of course this works
due to implicit conversion so this kind
of looks like identical code but the
difference is that this will actually
get destroyed once we go out of scope
because of course the scoped pointer
class itself the scoped pointer object
gets allocated on the stack which means
that it gets deleted and when it gets
deleted automatically equals delete in
the destructor which deletes that that
pointer that it's wrapping so if we put
a breakpoint here and hit f5 will
advance one line forward check our
console we see we can see the work-ready
mantasy and then one line forward again
and check this out we destroyed our
entity even though we use new to
heap-allocated
and that is a great example of first of
all what a very basic smart pointer
called unique pointer does we're going
to have an entire video dedicated to
smart pointers various
you know people have been like people
have been complaining about me using new
and not using smart pointers and
teaching bad C++ we're gonna have a real
little chat about that later by the way
but for all of you waiting for smart
pointers we're definitely gonna do a
video on that very very soon because
they're a very important part of the
language so this kind of automatic
creation an automatic destruction that
we can kind of get from the fact that a
stack based variable goes out of scope
and gets destroyed is actually really
useful and there are plenty there are
plenty of more examples just to name
another one off the top of my head a
timer let's just say you wanted time how
long you are inside a scope for
benchmarking or something you could
write a time a class which starts the
timer upon construction of the object
and that stops the time I maybe prints
the result or whatever when the object
when the timer object gets destroyed so
suddenly you've got an automatic timer
you just write one line of code at the
beginning of your function and that
entire scope is going to now be timed
and you turn and you never have to call
time it'll stop or whatever manually
because as soon as it goes out of scope
and calls that for you automatically
it's really amazing and there's so many
uses for it another one is mutex locking
if you want to lock a function so the
multiple threads can't access it at the
same time and caused an explosion you
can have an automatic scoped lock which
at the beginning of the function locks
it and at the end of the function
unlocks it and the Reds are coming soon
I really can't wait to get into the more
kind of complicated and fun stuff in C++
so don't you worry many more videos are
coming hope you guys enjoyed this video
if you did you hit that like button I
think is in that corner I will always
pointing over there and all the other
videos but I think it's here so now that
you know where it is you can click it
you can also help support this series on
patreon by going to patreon at home for
sash the churner there's plenty of cool
rewards that you can get access to such
as a private discord chat where we plan
these videos you can request whatever
you like you can ask me any questions
you want there as well and I of course I
I of course answer all of my patrons
because why wouldn't I but the most
important thing you do by supporting is
just making sure that I can make more of
these videos and get them out as fast as
possible so a huge thank you to all of
my supporters on that I will see you
guys next time I think next time we're
gonna finally talk about smart pointers
because well
yeah I'll see you guys next time goodbye
[Music]